Guide to the Stanford University, Department of Computer Science, Films F0110
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford University, Department of Computer Science, films
1968-1977
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford University. Computer Science Department
F0110
22 film reel(s) (16mm)
Information about Access
Open for research. Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Biographical/Historical note
The Department of Computer Science was established in 1965.
Stanford University. Computer Science Department
- Films
  - G. Podnar, "Don't Blame the Computer", 1977; 110.1; 1 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 1)
    Podnar, G.
  - D. I. Okhotsimsky and A. K. Platonov, "A Soviet Ant Takes a Walk", 1972; 110.7; 1 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    A dislpay simulation of a 6-legged ant-like walker getting over various obstacles. The research is aimed at a planetary rover that would get around by walking.
    By D.I. Okhotsimsky, et al, Insitute of Applied Mathematics -- USSR Academy of Science, titles translated by Stanford AI Lab and edited by Suzanne Kandra.
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    B/W, silent, 10 minutes
    Okhotsimsky, D. I.
    - Copy, 1972; 110.2; 1 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 1)
  - "Automated Pump Assembly", 1973; 110.3; 1 film reel(s) (16mm); color, silent, 7 minutes (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Shows the hand-eye system assembling an automobile water pump, using vision to locate the pump body and to check for errors. The parts are assembled and screws inserted, using some special tools designed for the arm. Some titles are included to help explain the film.
    Richard Paul, Karl Pingle, Bob Bolles, Vic Scheinman, Les Earnest, John McCarthy
    Scheinman, Victor.; Pingle, Karl.; Paul, Richard.; Earnest, Les; Bolles, Robert.; McCarthy, John, 1927-2011
    - Automated Pump Assembly (outtakes), 1973; 110.22A; 2 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 2)
    - Automated Pump Assembly, 1973; 110.22B; 1 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 2)
    - Automated Pump Assembly, 1973; 110.22D; 1 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 2)
  - Dialog with a robot, 1971; 110.4; 1 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 1)
    Presents a natural language dialog with a simulated robot block- manipulation system. The dialog is substantially the same as that in Understanding Natural Language.
    Winograd, Terry.
  - Ray Reddy, D. Espar, and A. Eisenson, "Hear, Here", 1969; 110.6; 1 film reel(s) (16mm); color with sound, 15 minutes (Box 1)
    This film describes the state of the speech recognition project as of Spring, 1969. A discussion of the problems of speech recignition is followed by two realtime demonstrations of the system. The first shows the computer learning to recognize phrases and the second shows how the hand-eye system may be controlled by voice commands. Commands as complicated as 'Pick up the small block in the lower lefthand corner', are recognized and the tasks are carried out by the computer controlled arm.
    Describes the state of the speech recognition project as of Spring 1969. A discussion of the problems of speech recognition is followed by two real time demonstrations of the current system. The first shows the computer learning to recognize phrases and second shows how the hand-eye system may be controlled by voice commands. Commands as complicated as "pick up the small block in the lower lefthand corner" are recognized and the tasks are carried out by the computer controlled arm.
  - "Programmable Assembly, Three Short Examples", 1974; 110.10; color, sound, 8 minutes; 3 sound tracks (Box 1)
    The first segment demonstrates the arm's ability to dynamically adjust for position and orientation changes. The task is to mount a bearing and seal on a crankshaft. Next, the arm is shown changing tools and recovering from a run-time error. Finally, a cinematic first: two robot arms cooperating to assemble a hinge.
    Scheinman, Victor.; Bolles, Robert.; Pingle, Karl.; Paul, Richard.
    - Duplicate copy, 1974; 110.5; 1 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 1)
    - Duplicate copy, 1974; 110.11; 1 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 1)
    - Duplicate copy, 1974; 110.12; 1 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 1)
    - Copy no. 5, 1974; 110.9; 1 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 1)
    - Soundtrack 1, 110.10A; 1 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 1)
    - Soundtrack 2, 110.10B; 1 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 1)
    - Soundtrack 3, 110.10C; 1 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 1)
  - Unidentified, 110.13; 1 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 1)
  - Orbital skyhooks: The Elegant Route to Space, 1977; 110.14; 1 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 1)
    Two parts of computer simulation depicting a dynamic orbital skyhook, a cable in a sub synchronous orbit that rotates to touch the planet surface. The first part shows a touch down and take off of an end of the cable at a hypothetical space port in Africa. The second segment shows an animated diagram of the cable skyhook as it rotates and orbits to "walk" the planet surface. Shot directly off a video monitor - low image quality.
  - Brian Harvey, "Display Terminals at Stanford", 1975; 110.15; 1 film reel(s) (16mm); B/W, sound, 13 minutes (Box 2)
    Although there are many effective programs to use display terminals for special graphics applications, very few general purpose timesharing systems provide good support for using display terminals in normal text display applications. This film shows a session using the display system at the Stanford AI Lab, explaining how the display support features in the Stanford monitor enhance the user's control over his job and facilitate the writing of display-effective user programs.
  - A. Eisenson and G. Feldman, "Butterfinger", 1968 Mar; 110.16; 1 film reel(s) (16mm); color, sound, 8 minutes (Box 1)
    Describes the state of the hand-eye system at the Artificial Intelligence Project in the fall of 1967. The PDP-6 computer getting visual information from a television camera and controlling an electrical-mechanical arm solves simple tasks involving stacking blocks. The techniques of recognizing the blocks and their positions as well as controlling the arm are briefly presented. [2 copies]
    - Use copy, 1 optical disc(s) (dvd); 1 optical disc(s) (DVD) (Box 110.16U2)
    - Butterfinger--Outtakes, 110.16; 1 film reel(s) (16mm)
      - Use copy, 1 optical disc(s) (dvd); 1 optical disc(s) (DVD) (Box 110.16U1)
  - Unidentified, 110.17; 1 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 2)
  - "Motion and Vision", 1972; 110.18; 1 film reel(s) (16mm); color, sound, 26 minutes
    A technical presentation of three research projects completed in 1972: advanced arm control by Richard P. Paul [AIM-177], visual feedback control by A. Gill [AIM-178], and representation and description of curved objects by G. Agin [AIM-173].
    Kandra, Suzanne.
    - Use copy, 1 optical disc(s) (dvd); 1 optical disc(s) (DVD) (Box 110.19U)
    - Duplicate copy, 110.19; narrative track only (Box 2)
  - "Hands", 1972; 110.20; 1 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 2)
    Stanford gold arm, (SAIL Vic Scheinman) stacks four small colored cubes at three sites on a black table cloth.
    Bolles, Robert.
  - Stanford Cart, 110.22C; 1 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 2)
  - Lunar Vehicle Remote Control: A Study by Stanford University Mechanical Engineering Design Division (3:54), 1966; 110.21; 1 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 1)
    - Outtakes (35:24), 110.8; 1 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 1)
      - Use copy, 1 optical disc(s) (dvd); 1 optical disc(s) (DVD) (Box 110.8U)